Guide to the Frank Knight Sanders Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Frank Knight Sanders Papers
1815-1953
RG 122
Yale University Divinity School Library
6
(13 boxes)
The papers include letters from Sanders' parents describing missionary work in Ceylon (Sri Lanka), correspondence and personal diaries of Sanders, writings, genealogical material, and photographs. There is also documentation related to Sanders' uncle, Henry Martyn Knight, who was the founder of the Connecticut School for Imbeciles. The son of ABCFM missionaries to Ceylon (Sri Lanka), Frank Knight Sanders (1861-1933) taught at Jaffna College, Ceylon from 1882 to 1886. He was on the faculty of the Yale Divinity School from 1891 to 1907, serving as Dean from 1901 to 1905. He was President of Washburn College in Topeka, Kansas from 1908 to 1914 and Director of Missionary Preparation for the Foreign Missions Conference of North America from 1914 to 1927.
Sanders, Frank Knight, 1861-1933
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
1861 Born in Batticotta, Jaffna, Ceylon (Sri Lanka), fifth son of Marshall Danforth and Georgianna (Knight) Sanders, missionaries under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions
1865 Came to U.S., lived with his uncle, Henry Martyn Knight, in Lakeville, CT. Parents returned to Ceylon.
1868 Mother died of pleurisy in Ceylon; father married Carrie E. Webb in 1870
1882 A. B., Ripon College, Wisconsin
1882-1886 Instructor at Jaffna College, Ceylon
1888 M.A., Ripon College, Wisconsin
1888 Married Edith Blackman; children: Helen, Morris Blackman, Frank Knight.
1889 Ph.D., Yale
1889-1891 Assistant in Semitic Languages, Yale
1891-1892 Instructor in Semitic Languages, Yale.
1892-1894 Assistant Professor of Biblical Literature, Yale
1894-1901 Woolsey Professor of Biblical Literature, Yale
1901-1905 Professor of Biblical History and Archeology, Yale
1901-1905 Dean of Yale Divinity School
1902 Ordained as Congregational minister in New Haven
1905-1908 Secretary of the Congregational Sunday School and Publishing Society
1908-1914 President of Washburn College, Topeka, Kansas
1914-1927 Director of Missionary Preparation for the Foreign Missions Conference of North America.
1933 Died in Rockport, MA
Scope and Contents
The Correspondence of Series I includes letters written by Sanders' parents that describe mission work and native customs in Ceylon (Sri Lanka) and give an interesting portrayal of world conditions in the third quarter of the 19th century. While in Ceylon from 1882 to 1886, Sanders received letters from his missionary brothers: Charley in Turkey and Will in Angola. During the period 1926 to 1932 Sanders attempted to trace his family history and received letters from family members supplying applicable information. Correspondence of 1925 includes letters to and from John R. Mott.
The Diaries and Journals in Series II include forty-four personal diaries of Frank Knight Sanders as well as journals describing trips taken by Sanders. The Writings of Series III include lectures, sermons, and articles by Sanders as well as writings of others. Writings by others include extracts from letters written by a Civil War doctor in 1862, anonymous sermons dating from 1815 to 1845, and medical sketches on the subject of "imbeciles" written by Henry Martyn Knight, superintendent of the Connecticut School for Imbeciles. The Printed Material of Series IV includes newspapers clippings, and miscellaneous pamphlets; a few pamphlets related to the Board of Missionary Preparation have been placed in YDSL HR1052. Series V, Personal Items and Memorabilia, contains biographical material, photographs, and genealogical information tracing Sanders' family back to early settlers of America, including Roger Williams of Rhode Island.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1846-1953
II. Diaries and Journals, 1878-1933
III. Writings, 1815-1929, n.d.
IV. Printed Material, 1920-1931, n.d.
V. Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1870-1933, n.d.
Missions -- Sri Lanka; People with mental disabilities -- Institutional care -- United States -- History; Sanders, Frank Knight, 1861-1933; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions -- Sri Lanka; Board of Missionary Preparation; Connecticut School for Imbeciles; Yale University. Divinity School
- Correspondence, 1846-1953; Series I
  - From Marshall Danforth Sanders to family members, 1846-1847 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - From Marshall Danforth Sanders to family members, 1851-1852 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members, 1853 Mar-Nov (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members [typescript copies], 1854 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members [49 page compilation - typescript copies], 1855- 1857 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members [typescript copies], 1856-1868 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members, 1856, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members, 1866, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - From Marshall and Georgianna Sanders to family members, 1868 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - From Marshall Sanders to Frank Knight Sanders, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - From Marshall and Carrie Sanders to Frank Knight Sanders, 1870,1871 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - To FKS from Carrie Sanders, brother, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - To FKS from brothers in Turkey, Angola, 1882, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - To FKS from brother in Turkey, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter appointing FKS Dean of YDS, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - To/from FKS, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - FKS to/from John R. Mott, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Incl. re. family history, 1926-1932 (Box 1, Folder 19-23)
  - To/from Morris B. Sanders, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Incl. corres. of Henry Martyn Knight re. Connecticut School for Imbeciles, 1868-1886, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Diaries and Journals, 1878-1933; Series II
  - Diaries/journals of Frank Knight Sanders, 1878-1904 (Box 2, Folder 27-29)
  - Diaries/journals of Frank Knight Sanders, 1905-1913 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Diaries/journals of Frank Knight Sanders, 1914-1919 (Box 4, Folder 31-32)
  - Diaries/journals of Frank Knight Sanders, 1920-1929 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Diaries/journals of Frank Knight Sanders, 1927-1933 (Box 6, Folder 34)
- Writings, 1815-1929, n.d.; Series III
  - Lecture and sermon notes of FKS
    - No. 5461: "Congregationalims: its Rise, History, and Achievements", 1924-1925 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Nos. 5498, 5500: incl. re. Wisdom literature, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - No. 5501:"The O. T. Viewed Historically", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Nos. 5503-5509: incl. re. Hebrew history, Apocalyptic literature, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Nos. 5511-5521: incl. re. missions and education, 1909-1913, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Nos. 5522-5528: incl. re. education of missionaries, church history, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 40)
    - Nos. 5529-5537: miscellaneous sermons, 1910, 1927, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 41)
    - Nos. 5538-5548: incl. re. missions and education, 1909-1914, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 42)
    - Nos. 5673-5675: re. Old Testament, 1921-1925, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 43)
    - Nos. 5676-5776: re. Bible, 1920-1923, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 44)
    - Nos. 5777-5799: incl. re. missions, world situation, 1917-1927, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 46)
    - Nos. 5800-5819: miscellaneous, 1915-1929, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - Nos. 5820-5827: incl. re. missions in Africa, miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - No. 5828: re. Old Testament, n.d. (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - Nos. 5830-5862: miscellaneous, 1925, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 50)
    - Nos. 5863-5876: re. Lausanne conference, miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 51)
    - Nos. 5877-5927: re. education, Bible, missions, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 52)
    - No. 5927: "History of Education Before the Middle Ages", n.d. (Box 10, Folder 53)
    - Nos. 5928-5951: re. church history, 1922-1924 (Box 10, Folder 54)
    - Nos. 5959-5985: miscellaneous, 1915, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 55)
    - Miscellaneous, 1917-1925 (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - Incl. re. religious education, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - "Hebrew-Jewish Preparation for Christianity", n.d. (Box 11, Folder 58)
    - Incl. re. Bible and church history, 1926, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 59)
    - Fragments, n.d. (Box 11, Folder 60, 61)
    - Fragments, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 62, 63)
  - Articles and papers by FKS
    - "The Foreign Mission Enterprise of the Church: its Place and Scope Today" (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "The Historical Study of the Bible", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "The Life and Work of Henry Martyn Knight" in Addresses at the Dedication of The Knight Hospital of the Mansfield State Training School and Hospital at Mansfield Depot, Connecticut 18 October 1926 (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "Mission Instruction in the Theological Seminaries of North America", 1919 (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "The Preparation Needed for the Foreign Field", 1917 (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "Random Jottings of a Friendly Visitor" in The Chinese Recorder, 1918 Nov (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "Scholarship and Old Testament" in The Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1915 Nov (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - "The Secret of the Teacher's Growth", n.d. (Box 12, Folder 64)
    - Five papers on Christian work in Brazil and South America, 1925 (Box 12, Folder 64)
  - Writings of others
    - "Confucianism Today" by D. Willard Lyon, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 65)
    - By and about Henry Martyn Knight, re. treatment of the mentally retarded ("imbeciles") and the Connecticut School for Imbeciles., 1880, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 66)
    - "Extracts from Dr. Woods Letters" (Civil War doctor), 1862 (Box 12, Folder 67)
    - Holograph sermons (author unknown), 1815-1845 (Box 12, Folder 68)
    - Holograph writings (authors unknown), n.d. (Box 12, Folder 69)
- Printed Material, 1920-1931, n.d.; Series IV
  - Pamphlets re. Congregationalism, Unitarianism, town of Salisbury, Connecticut, 1920-1930 (Box 12, Folder 70)
  - Materials re. teaching of religion, 1923, n.d. (Box 12, Folder 71)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings (Box 12, Folder 72)
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings, 1920-1932 (Box 13, Folder 73)
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1921-1929, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 74)
- Personal Items and Memorabilia, 1870-1933, n.d.; Series V
  - Notebook: "Family History Data: I Jaffna 1852-1864", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 75)
  - Notebook: "Family History Data: II 1864-", n.d. (Box 13, Folder 76)
  - Genealogical material, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 77)
  - Biographical information re. the Knight family, 1912, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 78)
  - Documents re. Henry Martyn Knight, 1870, 1880 (Box 13, Folder 79)
  - Documents re. estate of Kate B. Knight, 1928-1929 (Box 13, Folder 80)
  - Biographical material re. FKS, 1905-1933, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 81)
  - Miscellaneous, incl. poem from FKS to his wife, 1888-1917 (Box 13, Folder 82)
  - Photographs, incl. family photos and re. early mission work in Ceylon and India, 1884-1923, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 83)